Lee Child, the man behind the Jack Reacher series,
a series that sold more than 200 million books,
the best-selling series of all time on Amazon
in the UK. Yeah, more than Harry Potter,
which is crazy. And also a series where a
new book is sold on average every nine seconds.
So how does he do it? How does he write
it? How does he come up with the ideas? Well, here
Be
answers. You know where I want to start
the interview is creating a sense of place. Like,
obviously, you're English, you were in England when
you got fired, and then you're like, hey,
let's go base a story in America. So first of all,
why'd you do that? But also, how do you make that
real and vivid? I did it because for a
bunch of reasons that all pushed in the same direction.
One was that, as you say, I'd just been fired.
And it was a kind of political thing whereby the
TV industry in Britain was being altered
externally in order to give Rupert Murdoch
a foothold for his satellite business. So that
I was just annoyed, you know, really just pissed
off with what had happened. So in a lot of ways,
I wanted to escape. I was done with it. I wanted
to get out.
And if I couldn't do that yet physically, at least
I could do it in my head in terms of narrative.
And I had, when I started out writing, and this
is something that a lot of readers don't want to
hear, but writing is not just the muse, you
know, you don't sit down compelled to just write. It's
a job. And especially because I'd been fired, it
was a serious thing. I had to make a living.
And in order to do that, I had to make a living.
And I had to make a living. And I had to make a
career. And a lot of people think, you
know, you're saying it as an introvert. Well, no,
go ahead and answer.
In the gebe successes I had to have, I
had to, it wasص when I Haunted mama's house
as the Drive-Thru shops actually they all have
an elevator and nine girls can't get in there.
It was a Marvel movie.
John ammoniz a standoff.
We were the last thing that I
thought of when we were at tons.
He said to me and
was kind of sc服' at it.
We were nothing like if lines or масло member said to me a bottom Dilma b
조금 Western comedy of 2 necessities a lot of the mothers started looking towards the drama industry.
Carlos Cavalcante because he's not in any position
to be in the on a unexpected position.
reading out of Britain at the time, Barbara
Vine, who was, that's a pen name for Ruth
Rundell, and it was a certain kind of fiction
she was doing, very much in a couple of streets
in North London.
You know, that was the world.
You look at Ian Rankin, another great British crime writer.
That's literally like a couple of square miles in Edinburgh.
It was very internal in their heads, very small geography.
And I thought, my heart wasn't in that.
I wanted something that was a lot more related
to myth and legend from the past, the idea
of the mysterious stranger, the noble
loner who shows up here and there.
And for that, you need a
gigantic geography to make it plausible.
The idea that a stranger can wander miles.
Into a community that is effectively isolated and
cut off and has mystery and intrigue going
on, unbeknownst to the rest of the world.
That is not plausible in Britain.
Everybody knows everybody else's business.
Everybody lives cheek by jowl.
You needed that frontier field.
So it really had to be
America from the narrative point of view.
And I had been a lot.
I first went to the
US more than 50 years ago.
Now, and I eventually in 1974, I eventually
emigrated in 1998, which was 24 years later.
And part of the immigration procedure, if you
do it legally, is to apply in numerous
forms to fill out.
And one of them is you've got to
list every previous visit you've made to the US.
So I guess so they can check with police
departments here and there that you're not some kind of
murderer or something.
And so I had to go
back through all my old passports.
And in those 24 years, I'd
visited the US exactly 100 times.
Whoa.
Because my wife is from there.
And so every trip we took.
She's from where?
She's from New York.
Oh, okay.
So I, I felt I knew the country well enough to
write about it with the advantage of doing it with an
outsider's eye, which I think is huge.
I think that, uh, you run the risk of getting.
Details wrong.
You run the risk of sort of not quite
connecting with the culture, but there's an enormous advantage
in you're seeing things fresh.
You're seeing things that Americans no
longer see because they're so familiar.
And as you go about creating a sense of
place, what are the things that you're thinking about?
I mean, I don't know.
There's different, uh, instruments you can play.
You could play the instrument of sound.
You could play the instrument of sight.
You could play the instrument of light.
You could play the instrument of color of the
way the sun sets and rises in the morning, whatever.
Yeah.
Whatever it is.
How do you think about bringing a sense of place?
That's a life.
Good question.
And for me, I would say mostly it's temperature.
Uh, you know, I never heat versus cool.
Yeah.
Hard versus soft, hot versus cold.
Things like that.
I don't plan.
I never have a, you know, I don't, I'm not one of these guys that has a list of the
next eight plots, you know, the little index card saying, you know, set, set this one in main or something.
I don't do that.
What I do.
And this sounds terribly pretentious, but if you were a composer writing
music, you start with a concept of the key that you want.
Uh, you know, G major is a cheerful upbeat key.
Uh, E flat minor is, is the
opposite, you know, down and rather melancholy key.
So what I do as a writer is
I, I have a, just a vague idea.
I want this to be hard and
cold, or I want this to be.
Hot.
And then you pick a location
that you have been familiar with.
I never do research specifically for that book.
It always draws on impressions formed over
the years from previous visits to places.
Uh, you know, do you want it to be the
west of Texas where it is baking hot and arrowed?
Do you want it to be on the Atlantic coast
of Maine in April where it's gray and cold and misty?
So.
That's how I start with the sense of place.
And then it's just constructing it around that in a way, the
place and the temperature kind of dictates the story in a way.
Hmm.
Almost as if they're like the driving factors.
Yeah.
Or it gives you a stage on which
certain action is inevitable and certain is implausible.
Hmm.
Like almost sets the physics of the story.
I think it does.
Yeah.
You know, is it, is it mostly an indoor story?
Is it an outdoor story with, with wandering?
Is it.
Uh, just the flavor of it.
I'm absolutely not a planner and I
never have a preconception really of what.
Why do you say that with such emphasis?
Because a lot of people
assume that a book needs planning.
Hmm.
They assume that you write out an outline or at least a hit list
of, of, uh, plot points, some kind of a synopsis or outline or plan.
And I've never, ever done that.
I, I, I just.
Cause for me.
Writing per se, making it with words
is not really the issue for me.
It's the story that I want.
And if I were to plan a story and I've
got friends who do huge outlines, you know, 300 page outlines.
Even if I did a two page outline with, you know, two lines per proposed
chapter, then I've told myself the story and I'm bored with it at that point.
I want the next story.
So I can't afford to tell
myself the story ahead of time.
I have to just improvise it as I go along.
So it's about starting somewhere, which is
defined by location and then see what happens.
It's it really is that simple.
Yeah.
In your life, who were the writers who
you've made a point to read everything they've written?
Oh, lots and lots of them.
I mean, uh, there was a
British, uh, Scottish actually thriller writer.
God.
Alasdair McLean, who was huge when I was
a kid and, and really appealed to me.
I read everything in his.
What'd you take from him?
I took from him actually something I've used two things.
I took from him actually.
Number one was he had a real skill of having a
hero that was so good that he was almost the cartoon character.
He was almost falling off the edge
of being ludicrous and yet never did.
He just kept him the right side of plausibility.
And I learned that the other thing I learned was a completely negative thing that he got
drunk and lazy and bored after about eight books and fell off a cliff in terms of quality.
So I learned to avoid that.
If you can John D McDonald, who is, uh, was a Florida writer, did 21 books in the Travis McGee
series, which is really one of the most magnificent series and pulls up a trick that I, I cannot explain.
There was 21 books.
As I said, I.
There's an only one of them.
Only one of them has anything happen on page
one and the other 20, nothing happens on page one.
Nothing really happens on page two,
but you cannot put them down.
Now explain that to me.
I can't.
What happens in the first few pages?
Just two guys hanging out chatting or whatever, you
know, and, uh, somehow it's too, it's so compelling.
One of them, they're sitting in a boat page one,
they're sitting at night fishing in a boat on a canal.
In.
In South Florida, you know, they're chatting for half a page and then all of
a sudden somebody throws a body off the bridge and it lands in their boat.
That's the only story where something happens on page one.
And yet all of them are utterly addictive.
You literally kind of put them down.
How do you think your career, your writing unfolded differently by virtue of having one character who you brought in over
and over again versus, Hey, I'm going to do this story with all these characters, this story with all those characters.
Yeah.
It's a great question.
And again, I think an awful lot of it
depends on what turns you on as a reader.
I think you can't get away from that.
I think that if you find a guy who has enjoyed reading a certain genre
or a certain style within a genre, that is what they've got to write, really.
And again, from the audience's point of view, everything I
do, I try to remember how I felt as a reader.
What really turned me on as a reader?
How did I feel as a reader?
And with a series with a strong recurring
character, there's a kind of pre-approval amongst the readers.
Mm-hmm .
If they've tried one and liked it, then they're very
happy that the same guy comes back in the second book.
And then they understand it's turning into a
series where he's going to keep on coming back.
So every year, they get the new book.
And it is quite a change.
Yeah.
pre-approved in their mind. They know
they're gonna like it. They know they
want to read it. Certainly they want
a different plot, they want a different
context, all that kind of thing, but
they really want the familiarity and the
comfort of their old friend coming to
visit for a couple of days, hanging out
with the guy for a couple of days.
They'd love that. So to me series were always
super appealing as a reader so naturally I
wanted to write a series and I think
it works really well. That you know I've
got a lot of other writers I love, Stephen
King for instance. Now Stephen, he's a
great writer, terrific guy, great writer. I
mean literally America's greatest living novelist
I think at this point. I think
so. But Stephen King comes out with a
new book, you're never quite sure what it's
gonna be. Mm-hmm. Is it this? Is it
that? Is it horror? Is it supernatural? Is it
some other thing? You don't know. You
buy it because you love Stephen King, you
don't know. You don't know the story, you
don't know the story. You don't know the
story, you don't know the story. You
don't buy it because you know you're gonna
love the story because the story
could be anything at that point. Mm-hmm.
Obviously you famously start your books on
September 1st and so what is, how do
you sort of structure the year? How do
you structure the days in terms of where
that imagination comes into play? Where
the actual work of writing comes into
play and how those things come together? It's,
I get, yeah I do. I start on a
regular day which is
kind of necessary I think because if
you're gonna publish your book a year
clearly you've got to write a book a
year and you have got to have a certain
discipline and structure to you to do
that so it's totally convenient to pick
start 1st of September, deliver sometime in March
or April. That is the way to do
it and funny what you say there about
imagination because I, you know, I do a
book let's say I'm finishing it in
March or April, done, fantastic, happy with it,
and then I suffer a kind of
self-doubt. Well not really, it's not that I'm
sitting there racked with doubt but I
just, it kind of fades away. I've done
that book, I know it's some months before I
have to start the next one and kind of
July, August, beginning of August I'm thinking, oh
I've got to start in six weeks or
whatever and I'm just bereft, no ideas. I
thought, every year I think this is it,
I'm washed up now.
It was the previous 20 years was just
luck, you know, I've got nothing to do,
nothing to say, but no idea and I
feel a little despondent about it and then sure
as eggs are eggs, towards the end of
August I'm thinking, well you know I could,
yeah this might be cool or and then
toward again a few days later I have a
first line suddenly pops into my head so
by September the 1st I'm up and running
again. But the imagination somehow is biddable.
It, you know, it's a bit of a challenge.
You can quiet it down and you can
crank it up depending on when you need to.
Before we started recording you're like, yeah
I don't walk much, don't work out, love
to smoke cigarettes and all that and how
do you think that what you've produced is downstream
of how you've lived your life? Because
that is unique. Like it's this funny combination
of when you said that I was, my very
dear friend, he's just like, I'm just the laziest,
I'm just the most, you know, I'm just the
most, you know, I'm just the most, you know,
I'm just the most, you know,
I'm just the most, you know, God.
And I'm like, no way they're
going to let me do that.
You ever, you know, for those who are
listening, and if we are doing all the
察 news, I'm ignorance, you know, could
you just come close to our Gorilla Buzz
and call me Okay, no.
What if you have two, let's say,
bands in the audience, and they're COM.
I'm an expert diagonally and
think we need to get all the way
there in the East and then mesh in place.
I'm an expert, you know, coming in and
out of town I'm all like, Hey, can grazers
have the space so, you know, Charlie Brown,
if you want, I believe, should I better leave
the house.
Yeah, sorry.
Make it a it's fine.
a dull and very boring, repressive family
environment where there seemed to be an unspoken
target of just living as long as you possibly
could, taking care of yourself so that you live
to a grand old age. And I remember associating
that with the boringness of it. And I remember
literally at the age of eight, literally the age of
eight, I thought to myself, I'm not going to do
that. I'm just going to do whatever the hell I
want. And I don't care what the result will be.
My target is to have more fun in 60
years than the rest of them would have in 100.
So I've always done that. I live recklessly. I do
whatever I want to do. I pay no attention to
consequence or health or anything like that. And
it's an antidote, I think, to the repression
and that uptight upbringing.
Absolutely. In my family, smoking was regarded as just
awful, a terrible thing to do. And I don't
think... My parents were kind of before the
era of exercise. I mean, nobody in that generation,
nobody thought of taking exercise. But you
did naturally, I suppose, because maybe you didn't
have a car, so you had to walk to
work or whatever. But yeah, anything worthy, anything virtuous,
anything like that.
Anything like that.
I turned my face against. I didn't want
to participate in that kind of scheme. I just
wanted to live for pleasure. And I was also
very aware that I was a very lucky generation.
My micro generation, my birth year, maybe a
couple of years before, maybe a couple of years
afterward, was probably the luckiest
generation in all of human history.
Especially being born in Britain. We didn't even have
Vietnam. Yeah, we were born to a stable post-war
European democracy with national health service that
worked back then, with a welfare state that
worked back then. We had free education
completely. All the major dread diseases were conquered.
We never had to go to war. We never had
a bomb dropped on our house. We never had the secret
police knocking on the door. We never had a bomb
dropped on our house. We never had a bomb dropped
on our house. We never had a bomb dropped on
our house. We never had a bomb dropped on our house.
All those horrors that had existed very
recently no longer applied to us. And the
creativity that you saw exploding in Britain in
the 60s, for instance, all those great bands and
the great artists and photographers and fashion design,
all that stuff was because that was the
first free generation. It wasn't that they
suddenly developed all that talent. All that
talent had been around. And every generation had
been around. And every generation had been around.
regeneration, except it had been disallowed. They had to
go work in the factory. They had to go to
war. They had to do whatever.
And now the conditions were right.
The conditions were right. We didn't have
to do that stuff. So it did explode.
You know what? The word that came
to mind was just kind of unapologetic,
because there's the unapologetic in terms of,
yeah, you're supposed to do this. You're supposed
to do that. I don't really do the things that
I'm supposed to do. But then the other thing is just
the unapologetic decision to write in a commercial fashion.
To say, hey, this is my job. A lot of
writers are like, oh, don't do that. And it's
funny, you wouldn't walk into a hedge fund or
an investment firm and say, hey, don't try to
make as much money as you can. But somehow you
get into a library or a writer's
room and it's like, oh, don't say that.
In a way, it was because I started
out in the theater. That was my first enthusiasm,
my first love.
This before TV.
Yeah. Theater before TV.
And I remember that, say, 1971, 72, that kind
of time in theater, there was some great stuff,
but there was also some ridiculous crap. And a
lot of the ridiculous crap was kind of boasted about.
And people would say, you know, people would
put on terrible shows and get zero audience,
and they would be kind of proud
of it. Oh, you know, people don't understand
how...
Art and all that kind of thing. But I saw
it as a Zen proposition. If you put on a show
and nobody comes to see it, have you actually
put on a show? I'm not saying nakedly commercial
transaction, but the transactional aspect of it was
vital. It was integral. You put on a show,
somebody has to watch it before it exists.
If you write a book and nobody reads it,
have you written a book?
I had to include the audience in the calculation
so that I wasn't... It wasn't like a sort of
naked, meretricious thing where I was trying to make
a living, although I was trying to make a
living. But that wasn't forefront in my mind. It
was that if I'm doing something, I want people to
enjoy it. And if you want people to enjoy it,
you may as well have the maximum number of people
enjoy it. But of course, there's a technicality
about books and readership is that readership is
absolutely not moral. It's not moral. It's not
moral. It's not moral. It's not moral. It's not
monolithic. It is far more like the rings
of Saturn that even my books, any commercial
writer's books are consumed at the center
of that universe by very skilled, habitual readers.
And I've got all kinds of high grade, high level
fans. But in order to sell a lot of books,
you've got to push the boundary
outward to the outer rings of Saturn,
where the audience are people that read one
book a year, possibly two books a year.
And you've got to satisfy the
habitual, skillful, literate readers in the center
at the same time as satisfying the people
on the outskirts that are not habitual readers.
And so that is a skill
in itself to make a multi-level proposition.
And how does that play out? Like what is a...
How do you actually...
How do you think about structurally doing that?
I think structurally what you've got to
do is you've got to have a style
that is both palatable and somewhat enjoyable
to the habitual readers in the center,
but that is also useful to the
people on the outside. And that's inevitably,
that style needs to be therefore propulsive. I do a
lot of it instinctively, but I spend a lot of time
concentrating on rhythm, the rhythm of a sentence.
Because a book is however
many thousand sentences in a row,
and you've got to make it
so that each sentence has a rhythm,
and that rhythm must always
be tripping forward, forward, forward.
So this rhythm is less artistic and much
more about that word that you came back to,
propulsion, like the rhythm of
movement and progress and pace.
Absolutely.
Momentum.
It's about propulsion. It's as if...
It's as if I'm creating a style that the
experienced reader in the center appreciates as a style.
You know, call it whatever you want, faux naïve
or this or that, they'll find a word for it.
But the people on the outskirts, the non-habitual readers,
it's like I have my hand gently on their
back just pushing them through. They don't notice.
They're not aware of it, but I am
just easing them through the process.
And...
You know, one of the most heartfelt compliments
that you get, I've had dozens, hundreds of people
say to me, oh, I loved your book. I finished
it. It is such an achievement for some, you know,
not habitual readers, some unfamiliar, unaccustomed readers
to finish a book. It's a sense of
achievement, self-esteem, and so on. And you do
that by helping them finish the book. You push
them gradually through. You push them through the
process. You push them through the process. You
let them breathe. You push them through the
process. You push them through the process. They
don't notice, but you're driving them through it. And
you do that by propulsion, and you do the
propulsion by sentence structure so that the
beat is always tipping forward, forward, forward. It's
like a great pop song. If you look at
a great pop song back in the days before,
before, you know, all this electronic stuff came
along, the rhythm will speed up through the song
very, very, very subtly. Look at a Beatles
song, especially live. You know, Ringo will be driving,
in that drive in that tempo and it always
ends up a little faster than it begins. Nobody
notices but it's there and that's what you got
to do on the page. You've got to you got
to make it so that it's a little bit
like a like a carnival ride you know where you
it's they're slipping down this polished tube you
know and there's no getting out of it
once they're in it they can't get out.
And now tell me more about that sense of
propulsion because there you're talking about sentences
but then there's the sense of propulsion
of opening a question at the beginning keeping
that question open answering at the end. There's
the sense of propulsion that comes at the end
of a chapter of hey we're going to have
a cliffhanger. Television does this and in
the next episode you're going to learn something
like that. Yeah well that's and that's really where
I got it from I did 40,000 hours of
television of every kind and it kind of bakes
it into your DNA. And ending a chapter to
me is never thought about.
It is always
utterly sort of instinctively obvious. When you
say that do you mean that the book
begins to reveal itself that hey this is
where it should be or is it something else.
Yeah exactly you and even the end of a
book I remember one of my books the hard way
I think it was it was that book where
I remember finishing a chapter very late on and thinking
great you know I'm almost done I've just got
to kind of do I don't know maybe a chapter
and a half to wrap it up. And then I
suddenly realized no this is the end of the book. This
is done now.
Because you just know. It's all about asking
the question and TV had a thing there was
a situation in 1980 that changed completely
by 1990 by 1990 people had something that
they did not have in 1990
and it utterly changed the business.
And you see now you are thinking on television. At
leastiyorsun wasn't the robot you see on television, was it.
It was. lack of건
Now you are thinking, why?
What is he talking about?
What did they not have in
1980 that they did have in 1990?
I've implied a question there.
And you now want the answer.
And the answer is remote control.
In 1980, people actually physically had to get
up off the sofa and change the channel.
In 1990, they could do it
with the push of a button.
And that utterly changed the business.
And because you could rely on
a certain amount of laziness in 1980,
you could rely that if they finish one program,
they're going to stick around through
the commercial break for the next one.
By 1990, absolutely, all bets were off.
They could jump around at the press of a finger.
And that utterly changed it.
And so how did we react to that?
We reacted to it by
something that has largely disappeared now,
but you still see, for instance,
in baseball or certain sports where,
you know, in baseball,
you get to the sort of fourth inning and it's
pretty clear maybe which way the game's going and so on.
And so they usually have a trivia question
that they'll tell you the answer at the end
of the break when they return to the game.
And it's incredibly powerful that humans are
hardwired to want to know the answer,
even if they're not interested in the subject.
You know, if it's a movie
show or something, you might say,
who was the first choice for Dirty Harry?
In terms of casting, we'll tell you after the break.
And people are like, whoa, who was the first choice?
Wasn't Clint Eastwood the first choice?
And they want to know.
Even if they do know, they want to
stick around for the gratification of being proved right.
That's why people love Jeopardy.
Yeah.
And, you know, the answer to who
was first choice, believe it or not,
for Dirty Harry was Frank Sinatra.
He turned down the part.
So we learned that humans are hardwired to want,
the answer to a question.
And I think, actually, that is
the easiest part of constructing a novel.
Absolutely the easiest part.
You imply a question.
It doesn't matter what it is.
It doesn't matter how important it is.
People will stick around to find out the answer.
And so that really, plotting in that sense,
is way overestimated in terms of difficulty.
Plotting is really pretty easy.
And now, as a writer,
do you feel like you're going on an adventure yourself,
kind of like fingers are following the story or something?
Yeah, I mean, absolutely.
Again, I try and replicate.
What I want is this feeling
that I have as a reader.
And you know this.
When you've got a really great book on the go,
you're really angry if you have to put it down.
And you just cannot wait to get back to it.
You know, let's say you've got to
do a chore or an errand or something.
Or go to work.
And then you get back and you
pick up the book and you're like,
ah, what's going to happen next?
Yeah.
I need that feeling as a writer.
It's incredibly strong as a reader.
I remember one Christmas day,
I was, our daughter was working in a cinema.
And she was doing the day shift on Christmas Day.
And therefore, our Christmas was going to
start when she finished work and got back,
which was maybe, I don't know, six o'clock or something.
So I was reading a book.
That afternoon, it was a great book.
I was just loving it.
And I was thinking, I was hoping
that there would be a big snowstorm
and she couldn't get there or something like that.
I was hoping that she wouldn't arrive so
that I could keep on reading the book.
And that's the power of story.
And I want to feel that power when
I'm writing it as well as reading it.
Well, you were talking about needing
to know the answer to the question,
kind of being pulled along.
The other word that came to mind for me,
it was just the feeling of being absorbed.
Absorbed in another world, absorbed
in a pattern of language,
absorbed in characters and scenes.
Absolutely immersed, I call it.
And that is such a subtle thing.
I mean, how do you do it?
Nobody knows.
No, but I do.
It absolutely happens or it doesn't happen.
You know, that's one of the strange things,
there's all kinds of cliches, you know,
or jokes about how to write a book.
You know, people say a
thriller, it needs just two things.
Unfortunately, nobody knows what they are.
And that's kind of true.
I was so excited for you
to tell me what they were.
Exactly.
You know, it's a mystery.
Sometimes it grabs you and sometimes it doesn't.
Is that individual to the reader?
Is it general?
Can you trust it for a
large population as opposed to individual readers?
I don't know.
I think certain books appeal
to different people in different ways.
But yeah.
Either you are.
I think there's a lot of people
who are immediately sucked into the world.
And I think probably the way to
do that is not try too hard.
I think that is absolutely true
of practically every aspect of writing.
Don't try too hard.
There's a great, great quote by David Mamet, a screenwriter.
He was talking about actors in this particular quote,
but really it can be about book characters or anything.
And he said,
essentially,
if you're an actor who steps onto the
stage or steps onto the screen, and he says,
hey, I'm the main character.
And the audience says, are we going to like you?
And the worst possible answer
is to say, yes, you are.
And I'll tell you why.
That's the worst possible answer.
The best possible answer.
Are we going to like you?
I don't know.
And I don't care.
That is the.
That.
That is the way to do it.
And I think that's the way to do it.
Insouciance, self-confidence is the way to do it.
He was talking about that generation of actors
that had come out of the Korean War, people
like Gene Hackman and Lee Marvin and people like that.
They had a certain kind of self-confidence.
They were not needy.
They were just there.
Take me or leave me.
They weren't trying too hard.
And that in a strange roundabout way, the
less you worry about, are they going to like
you?
The more they do like you.
So help me reconcile a few things.
On one hand, what I'm hearing is
this sort of don't try too hard.
And then on the other side, it's a
real sense of discipline of treating your writing like
a job showing up every day.
Help me work that out.
Well it is.
I mean it is.
But writing is a strange thing in that you
have got to believe two things a hundred percent.
Both of them.
It's not believing one 50 percent, the other 50 percent.
You believe them both a
hundred percent, which is mathematically impossible.
You've got to do it.
You've got to believe it's artistic, it's creative,
it is noble, it's part of a great
tradition that stretches back a
few centuries now, writing novels.
You've also got to believe it is a
job that your family's income depends on, that you
have responsibilities to publishers and retailers.
You've got to believe both things 100 percent.
And so you do need structure.
You do need discipline.
Ultimately you owe it to the reader.
And that is what has
been the driving force for me.
Initially I'd lost my job, I
was broke, I was out of work.
And initially the implied contract was purely financial.
Could I keep a roof over my head?
Could I pay the bills?
And then when that turned out to be
yeah, you know, happily that happened, then it became
an emotional contract with the reader.
The reader has loved these books.
The reader has bought these books, enthused
about them, talked about them, enjoyed them.
So my obligation from that point
on was never to let them down.
And part of that, of course,
is actually showing up with the product.
Because if the reader, not just me of
course, but hundreds of series writers publish a new
installment every year, if you miss one,
the reader is really disappointed about that.
Okay, so we're talking about how
do you get your writing done.
And if you're thinking about work and, you
know, writing, you're going to have to do
a lot of work.
And how you can be more productive
there, well, I recommend a tool called Basecamp.
Basecamp is a project management tool.
And it's different from the other ones,
which are loud and noisy and cluttered, they're
feature bloat.
Basecamp says no, no, no, no, no, we're going
to keep things simple so that you can focus
on what actually matters, which is
just getting the work done, you know?
Now for us, Basecamp is a place where we
can track what we're doing with how I write, when
episodes are being recorded, where we're recording
them, the publishing day, all those sorts
of things in one place for
our entire team to look at.
And that's what Basecamp is all about.
And I had the founder of Basecamp, Jason
Fried, he came on the show, and I noticed
that he really cares about writing.
He cares about manifestos, he cares about
great copy, he cares about telling a great
story.
And him and his co-founder, they've written five books.
And I can tell you that they bring the
same care and attention to detail to their books
as they do their software.
So if you're thinking about work and you're
asking, hey, how can I be more productive?
How can I make my team more cohesive?
Well, then I recommend Basecamp.
All right.
Back to the episode.
And tell me about what
goes into making a main character.
Because you were talking about likability.
And is that important in the main character?
When is it good?
Hey, should we like the main character?
Should we hate the main character?
Should we think they're funny?
I don't think that you can
have a character that you hate.
A main character that you hate or a character?
Well, obviously a character, a despicable bad
guy or a henchman or something like that.
You can absolutely hate them.
But in terms of the main character...
Or the...
The implied main character, Hannibal Lecter, for
instance, would be as close as you could
get to a character that you should hate.
But there is something compelling about them.
You can have characters that you ought
to hate, but you kind of don't.
Which you're breaking bad.
Yeah.
All that noir style.
There's something about them that makes
them likable, even though you shouldn't.
You absolutely can't have a character designed to be hated.
Yeah.
You absolutely equally cannot have a character
that's designed to be liked because the more
you design it, the worse it gets.
You've just got to have an honest, authentic
portrayal, and then you've got to hope for
the best.
You know, when I'd start...
I did the first Reacher book, I thought...
And there's a clue in what I'm going to say.
I thought, I'm happy with this.
I love this.
You know, this is 100%
what I wanted it to be.
Obviously.
I would have done it differently.
This was exactly what I wanted.
But I thought, ah, nobody
else is going to like this.
The guy is a filthy, dirty barbarian.
He shoots people in the back.
He lies.
He cheats.
He steals.
He never changes his clothes.
Nobody's going to like this guy.
And then I thought, well, maybe some men
will like him, but women won't or whatever.
But the clue is I liked him.
Now.
I am obviously a unique individual, just like
you are, just like everybody else is, but
we're not that unique.
We all share quite a lot of culture together.
And so if I like him, the chances are
that many, many other people will like him too.
The only unknown at that point is how many exactly.
You know, is it going to be thousands?
Is it going to be hundreds of thousands?
Is it going to be millions?
You don't know that yet.
But if you like it, a substantial
proportion of other people will like it too.
What matters?
Let's bring together two themes.
We've been talking about rhythm propulsion.
And I think there we've been
talking about a kind of truth, right?
You're saying if you don't, if you plan
it, it's not going to kind of feel real.
There's something about the following the
roller coaster that actually makes it feel
real.
So bringing together the propulsion, the truth,
what matters in dialogue as you're writing
dialogue and bringing that to life?
Yeah.
I mean, dialogue is the ultimate kind of illusion.
In fact, I once...
I think once.
I won a competition prize or won some literary prize.
I think it was from...
It was years ago.
I think it was the Fort
Worth Evening Telegraph or something in Texas.
I won the prize for natural dialogue.
And honestly, written dialogue in a book,
there is nothing less natural than that.
It's really instructive to actually seriously
really listen to how people speak.
Yeah.
I mean, in a real dialogue exchange where
people are talking, go on the train and eavesdrop
at the seat next to you or whatever.
Listen to how people really talk.
It is incoherent.
It is stop, start.
It's absolutely full of placeholders.
You know, all this kind of stuff.
People jump from one subject to another.
There are long gaps.
It's utterly, utterly unlike anything
you will ever see written down.
In a book, it's...
It's...
In a book, it is utterly unnatural that
people talk in a structured way and actually exchange
information A, B, A, B like that.
It absolutely never happens in real life except you
can do it in a way that makes people think
it's utterly natural.
One of the greatest illusions in entertainment.
Again, rhythm is important because dialogue, when
you listen to people talk, they put emphasis
on words that vary throughout the sentence.
And how do you do that on the page?
In extremis, you can use italics,
I suppose, for the emphasized word.
I prefer not to because otherwise you've got
italics peppered over the entire page in random
spots.
You don't really want to do that, but you've
got to construct the rhythm in such a way
that the emphasis is thrown onto that word
as opposed to any other words so that you
go duh, duh, duh.
Somehow the rhythm lands you on the important word.
Yeah.
And I think that's what's so interesting about this.
I think it's partly an innate skill.
It comes from reading a lot.
It comes from listening a lot.
And it comes from-
Listening a lot.
How do you do that?
Like listen to people chat?
Listen to real people talk,
listen to movies, listen to TV.
I mean, there's a lot of great dialogue on TV.
There's a lot of great dialogue in the movies.
Just immerse yourself in it.
Listen, listen, listen.
And you pick it up how to do it.
Man, I was on the train
last night coming back from Gatwick.
And there was a woman sitting
next to me, an Indian woman.
She was with her husband.
And something had happened where she had lost a
bunch of money and she was in a financial
struggle.
And the way that she kept on
emphasizing the word money, I need my money.
I lost my money.
And just the tension of it.
It was just this, this, you talk
about listening, like there's a story there.
Absolutely.
And you've laid it out very well there
that you use a little bit of repetition.
I, I don't know.
I don't know.
But the fact that you have
a word, I need my money.
I have lost my money.
That creates it to a large extent.
The repeated words kind of dissolve in the
air and you've got need money, lost money.
The emphasis automatically ends up on those words.
Yeah.
You know, it's funny.
Now that you're saying it back to me in
moments of anger, there's a great simplicity in language.
I need my money.
I lost my money.
There's no room for the highfalutin, whatever.
It's you are in a primal state.
Yeah.
You are, and you also tend to
use that emphatic repetition of certain words
that almost then relates it to song in a way.
It's like lines in the chorus of a song,
which, you know, let's venture back into prehistory.
What was the first ever
art form had to be singing.
You know, we already had expressive voices
because of the development of
syntactical language in our evolution.
So obviously the first music was sung.
And singing depends on rhythm
and repetition to a large extent.
So we revert to it when
we are in an excess of emotion.
That's a great story.
I can absolutely picture that woman.
I can hear what she's saying, and
I would know how to write it.
Beginnings, endings, what matters as you're writing those?
You know, one of the beginnings and endings,
let's talk about beginnings and endings.
First of all, for you as
a writer, when should you begin?
When should you end?
And I find it very difficult
to, I get invited to, let's say,
a college somewhere or even a
high school to talk about writing.
And there's all these people keen on being writers.
And really the only valid message to them is,
don't, don't do it now.
Wait.
Too young.
Read for 20 years and then do it.
Because there's a lot of enthusiasm,
a lot of talent amongst young people,
but there's no content yet.
They haven't lived, they haven't
seen things, they don't know much.
You need to know when to start.
And you need to know when
to finish your career as well
before you get worn out and boring.
That's the macro sense.
And in the book, where do
you start and where do you finish?
You don't start when the earth cooled.
That is what a lot of beginning writers get wrong.
They start, they give you the back story.
You've got, let's say, you
have a great line of dialogue,
your character has a great line of dialogue.
They feel they need to tell
us about where you grew up,
where you went to school, who your parents were,
what formed you, all that kind of stuff.
Do not start when the earth cooled.
Start with the action right now.
There's a Latin phrase, in media
res, meaning in the middle of things.
Start in the middle of things.
Don't give all the explanation yet.
Just start with something intriguing and see where it goes.
And where do you end it?
You end it when the story's over.
How do you know when the story's over?
You've just got to judge that.
You've got to judge that on a gut level, instinctively.
One thing that does not work, I've tried this,
I've done a long series, and so
I've had room to experiment a little bit.
We had a thing in television,
see, television developed over the years
a tremendous amount that television used
to be what you would call
a series activity that you would
concentrate on TV before you did whatever
was next.
You would watch it on your TV
and you would do it in your day.
And your grandma still does it.
She sits and watches her show.
But most people don't do that.
It developed into a parallel activity in
as much as now you watch the show
while you're on the phone to
your mother, while you're cooking dinner.
In other words, and we went
through, we had to cope with that.
And so what we would do, we had
this sort of shorthand way of saying it.
would tell you that we're going to tell you. Then
we would tell you. Then we would tell you that we
told you. That sort of, in order to help
people who were very distracted. And I wondered, was I
doing that a little bit too much in the books?
And so I thought, I'm going to try and experiment
where I don't explain everything. I will
give the information. The information will be there,
hiding in plain sight, but I will not
pull it together and make the conclusion. I'll leave
that up to the reader. That happened in
one book very explicitly. In another earlier book,
there was quite a fascinating minor character, quite
a brave woman whose husband was in trouble
and she was brave about it and so on.
And I left it completely unstated what happened to her,
thinking that this character would live on in
the reader's mind and the reader would decide
for themselves what had happened to her.
Yeah.
I want you to do the
work and tell them the story.
You were talking about writing being a second
half of your life kind of thing, right?
The first half is about more indexed
towards collecting, reading, and picking up life experiences.
And then the writing comes a little bit later.
How do you think that varies across genres?
Because, like, intuitively, I'd be
like, hey, you're making up stories.
Why do you need to know stuff?
But no, no, no.
Clearly, I'm missing something in that assumption.
Yeah, I think what you need to—and nothing is
ever all one thing or all the other thing.
Sure, sure.
I mean, I know that in my genre, virtually everybody
that's successful is doing it as a second phase career.
Having done something prior that often does require an audience, either they're a journalist or they're a lawyer
with a jury in mind or something like that, and then they go on to be a writer.
There have been a couple.
There are people that have started fresh in their 20s, early or
mid-20s, that have made a success, but it's very much the minority.
And even though you might be inventing an entirely new genre, because an old guy like me, there's all kinds
of stuff, you know, vampire fiction, this, that, the other, that I have just no concept of what it's about.
But it's about something, and
it's about structure in a sense.
And so what you do have—
What you have to have is enough reading, I think, that you have
internalized the idea that there must be a structure and what structure is.
People are very skeptical when I say I
never make a plan, I never make an outline.
Every single line is improvised on
the spot, and that is absolutely true.
But it is not quite as naked as it
sounds because I've read tens of thousands of books.
So, in fact, I have an enormous internal—
I've read a database of virtually every available plot, virtually every
type of character, virtually every type of cliffhanger or structure or whatever.
I've got it in there somewhere.
So, actually, I have a monster plan and outline.
Yeah, I've been going down the rabbit
hole of just all sorts of different creatives.
And what you realize is that the bank of how much
they've consumed is just so much greater than people would realize.
Martin Scorsese.
He used to watch.
He used to watch a movie every single night.
You look at someone like Ralph Lauren.
People say, hey, you know, what was it
like talking to him in the early days?
He just knew every single thing
about the different kinds of ties.
Talking to a musician.
Musician was saying, hey, the way that you can
remember how things look, I can remember how things sound.
So I can tell you how Oman sounds
versus how Israel sounds versus how China sounds.
And you just realize that when you're talking
to great creatives, it is this process of constant.
Consumption.
But there's even more.
This very naturally created filing bank that
somehow you're pulling from without even realizing.
Absolutely.
In the process of creation.
That is very well put and very well diagnosed.
And that is exactly what happens that you.
I mean, for instance, I remember that the first
Jack Reacher movie with Tom Cruise directed by Chris McQuarrie.
McQuarrie.
I mean, man, that movie crews work hard.
You know.
It's 12, 14 hour day, maybe up
at five in the morning or whatever.
Work all day.
Incredible.
And then what would happen?
McQuarrie invites everybody to his suite and they watch a movie because
it's not that it's like a duty to top up their knowledge.
It is their enthusiasm.
But they end up, they
work all day making a movie.
Then they watch a movie.
And that internal database gets
bigger and bigger and bigger.
More.
And more passionately analyzed.
And you're absolutely right.
Whoever it is.
Interior designer.
They know this stuff because it's their life.
And writers are like that.
It's what we're total consumers.
Actually, we're not.
We're not predominantly a writer.
We're predominantly a reader.
You know, you write one book a year.
You read hundreds.
And so you're much more
of a reader than a writer.
So your internal supply.
You know.
Supply of reference and stimulation is by
the time you get halfway through your life.
Enormous by that point.
Violence.
Making it feel real.
The purpose of it.
What matters with violence?
I think making it feel real is again, it's a bit of
an illusion, a bit like dialogue in as much as most violence.
Most violence in the real world is over really quickly.
And most violence has got very bad medium term effects.
I mean, the thing that you see in the movies where or in a regular story where, you know, somebody is hit
hard and staggered back and then they come back at you and swing at you and back and forth, back and forth.
That does not happen in real life.
And I think that's the thing that's really important.
If you get hit in the head,
you are sick and dizzy for a week.
You know, you're just out of action.
Yeah.
I mean, also, if you watch the
average bar fight, it's just so lame.
It is.
It's just swiping and brawling.
There's no style to it.
There's no technique to it.
So again, violence is something
that is nowhere near realistic.
Um, and why do we, it's a really interesting question.
Why do we want it in a story?
Why do we like it?
And.
Uh, the answer to that, I think
is it is paradoxical because generally speaking out
of the population as a whole, people who
read books are the most thoughtful, probably the
most educated, the most, uh, in some way,
what you would call not virtuous, but you
know, they're on one side of the divide.
Why do they want violence in the book?
And I think it is because they know.
That in a civilized society.
You shouldn't have it.
You should have law.
You should have due process.
You should have rights for the accused.
People know that as that's the price of civilization.
That's how we organize ourselves.
They get that.
They understand it.
They approve of it.
They would not like to
see the real world any different.
But man, is it frustrating if somebody has stolen your
car, you just want to smash him in the face.
Oh yeah.
You don't want to go through all this.
Big old red hook.
Yeah.
You know, so that the real world that they're committed to, that they feel
like they, they need to have and support in a good, solid, liberal way.
And I don't mean liberal, uh, politically necessarily.
Lower case L.
Yeah.
I just mean in terms of modern civilization, they know that
we need these rules and safeguards, but it is terribly frustrating.
And so they love the consolation
of being in a fictional universe.
They know it's fictional.
But they love to see.
It happen as a release, as a consolation.
So then as you're writing violence and we're talking about
the illusion and bringing that to life, what matters there?
And do you feel like it's the same sort of thing
we're pulling from a reference bank of violent stories that you've read?
Yeah, largely.
And, and also lived, you know, cause I, I grew up in a, in
a very, it was a menu, huge manufacturing city and it was very, uh, inarticulate.
It was, uh, it was a very,
it wasn't the ideal place to live.
Some people were afraid of alguns translated words.
They let me do the trash.
The end in Korean laughs them from somewhere.
And I, you knew that it was like the ambient
of that passive social ogromizationacion of the local never best.
It was just a really scaring place.
I, I really enjoyed it.
Uh, it was quite a complicated.
And and so there was, there were
very serious leaders fighting all the time.
On peace process.
And there were the key
levels connecting people old and younger.
In my concept, human2016 was like the
northern program, which was a primary path level.
But at the time there was no social stuff.
And you know, I was, I seen it all.
All the people who were doing their jobs,
or said that people who couldn't work instead of
who were helping me.
ballet moves as it were for that but
mainly it's about tuning into uh people's secret hidden
desires and i when i did bookstore events or public
events i i used to have a line i said the
the reason why you like reacher is that
even though you are good citizens you are civilized
people you are all of the good things even though
you all have a list of 10 people you would
cheerfully shoot in the head and they do you know and
they see it happen on the page and it is a
release it is uh it is getting the
satisfaction without actually see without actually having it
in real life clothing clothing
is your writing how how does
clothing is your writing how how does
clothing inform character i think it is a symbol
you know it's a very quick way of describing a
type of person um that you we all have a
kind of internal comparative database of uh you know if
you see an old an old old guy with a
long gray ponytail and uh double denim you kind of know
who that person is yeah uh you see a
guy wearing um you know lace-up oxfords and and
and and pleated chinos or something like that you
know who that guy is there they are quick
references i think like teeth as well i once
had a fan who was a dental hygienist and she
would write in about every reference to the
appearance of people's teeth in books and i
found that fascinating because i realized i was
doing that instinctively again kind of trying to
come up a character through a quick visual
reference uh you know a snaggle tooth person a
person with missing teeth a person with a wolf-like
teeth or something like that um she was obviously
a professional and very interested in it and
was picking up on everything and i wasn't really
realizing i was doing it it was a shorthand
way of describing people all right we're uh you're
invited to a university you're given a semester to
teach a class on writing a seminar in writing how
you structure a class on writing how do you
structure a class on writing how do you structure
the curriculum what are the core things that you're
trying to tell people uh i would turn down
that gig i absolutely would i don't think i'm i
don't think i'm as good as as a teacher i'm pretty
sure that writing is not teachable i think
plenty of shortcuts within the business of writing are
totally teachable you know how to get a good agent
what pitfalls to avoid how to relate to a publisher
how to do this or that
i think absolutely that can be taught
based on experience of what has worked and what
hasn't but actually how to write i'm not sure
uh can be taught when you say not teachable
does that also mean not learnable or can something be
yes you can learn how to do it
but that doesn't mean that it can be taught
i i think you absolutely can learn to do it
and i would i would allow possibly the the possibility
that something that might take you 10 years of
reading before you figure it out for yourself could
take a little longer you could read
it and understand something of the original writing
and that's what this journey of very
different experiences means it's a journey naturally
i think being an Accounting
Internet link that you can click in to
as the screen opener it is right now
it is now a learning experience it is
life your experience with the world and today's
two-day journey going post мне
driver
an account
law
I've got musician friends.
In fact, I made a CD
with a couple of musician friends.
They did the music.
I did the lyrics.
Oh, cool.
Totally cool.
Just the best fun ever.
And hanging out with them, you know, structurally,
biologically, our brains are all the same, obviously.
But it's almost like there are little tubes that in my brain,
some of them are big and fat and can let things through.
And others are collapsed, you know, like
flat tires that nothing will get through.
And their brains are different.
They've got different tubes open and different tubes closed.
And it just, if you are a musician, you are.
And if you're not, you never will be.
Last question.
You're English.
Why has so much good writing
come from Scotland, from England, from Ireland?
What is it about this part of the world?
I think it's interesting.
Different answers for each of those different countries.
I think Scotland is, I mean,
England is the center of the UK.
And all the power lies exactly
where we are right now in London.
And I think Scottish people
feel neglected and resentful of that.
And so they build up an alternative culture that's theirs.
I think in Ireland, it's very clear in Ireland.
I love Ireland for this reason.
That if you go there.
So.
They,
they give you a chance.
Whoever you are.
You're not a writer is just some guy
you're in the pub with a bunch of.
Friends.
You start to tell a joke or you start
to tell a story, whatever they will give you a
chance.
Maybe it's only five seconds.
Maybe it's only 10 seconds, but you've.
The stage to state your case
and they will listen to you.
And I think that's that.
Uh, people grow up feeling that
when we're validated there's no fear.
Mm-hmm.
they will be heard, not for long if they're crap,
but they will give you the chance to be heard.
I think that's huge.
You know, that reminds me
of a bunch of Irish friends,
bunch of Irish friends.
I was trying to think about how were they different
from my American friends?
And the way that they're
the same is that, you know,
they're pretty career oriented,
but the way that they're different
is all of them to a T.
They know how to tell a joke.
They know how to tell a story.
Exactly.
And one of the things I
noticed that when I was in Ireland
is like, if you could go to the pub
and you can tell a good story
and you can keep people
engaged, you can make people laugh,
you can just hook them in and keep them there,
you're part of the squad.
Right, you are.
And you get to be that
because they give you the chance.
If you seize it, then you have the space,
you have the table, you know, you have the platform.
And I think that encourages them,
certainly emboldens people and encourages them
and they think, yeah, I can do this.
Well, you are welcome on How I Write anytime.
This was so fun.
It was great to meet you.
Good to meet you too.
And thank you very much for the opportunity.
Yeah.